http://www.gracech.org.uk/index.php?zonename=policies31

SafeguardingSafeguarding Guidance and PracticeWe seek to abide by the principles set out in the House of Bishops Policy Statement: "Promoting a Safer Church"We look to follow the guidance contained in the "Parish Safeguarding Handbook"Here is our current Safeguarding StatementContact Details:Our safeguarding team can be contacted on
Privacy policiesHere are our current Privacy Policies, click to downloadGeneral Privacy PolicyGENERAL PRIVACY NOTICEYour
personal data – what is it?“Personal data” is any information about a living individual which
allows them to be identified from that data (for example a name, photographs,
videos, email address, or address).
Identification can be by the information alone or in conjunction with
any other information.  The processing of
personal data is governed by [the Data
Protection Bill/Act 2017 the General Data Protection Regulation 2016/679 (the
“GDPR” and other legislation relating to personal data and rights such as the Human
Rights Act 1998].Who
are we?This Privacy Notice is based on the standard wording set out by
the Church of England and is provided to you by the Church
Council of Grace Church, Muswell Hill which
is the data controller for your data. Grace Church, Muswell Hill is a
charitable incorporated organisation registered with the Charity Commission
(charity no. 1185990)The Church of England is made up of a number of different
organisations and office-holders who work together to deliver the Church’s
mission in each community.  The Church
Council works together with:·
the Minister of Grace Church, Muswell Hill;·
the bishops of the Diocese of London; and·
the London Diocesan Fund, which is responsible for the financial
and administrative arrangements for the Diocese of London.As the Church is made up of all of these persons and organisations
working together, we may need to share personal data we hold with them so that
they can carry out their responsibilities to the Church and our community.  The organisations referred to above are joint
data controllers.  This means we are all
responsible to you for how we process your data.Each of the data controllers have their own tasks within the Church
and a description of what data is processed and for what purpose is set out in
this Privacy Notice.  This Privacy Notice
is sent to you by the Church Council on our own behalf and on behalf of each of
these data controllers.  In the rest of
this Privacy Notice, we use the word “we” to refer to each data controller, as
appropriate.What
data do the data controllers listed above process?  They will process some or all of the
following where necessary to perform their tasks:·
Names, titles, and aliases, photographs;·
Contact details such as telephone numbers, addresses, and email
addresses;·
Where they are relevant to our mission, or where you provide them
to us, we may process demographic information such as gender, age, date of
birth, marital status, nationality, education/work histories,
academic/professional qualifications, hobbies, family composition, and
dependants;·
Where you make donations or pay for activities such as use of a
church hall, financial identifiers such as bank account numbers, payment card
numbers, payment/transaction identifiers, policy numbers, and claim numbers;·
The data we process is likely to constitute sensitive personal
data because, as a church, the fact that we process your data at all may be
suggestive of your religious beliefs.  Where you provide this information, we may
also process other categories of sensitive personal data: racial or ethnic
origin, sex life, mental and physical health, details of injuries,
medication/treatment received, political beliefs, labour union affiliation,
genetic data, biometric data, data concerning sexual orientation and criminal
records, fines and other similar judicial records.How do
we process your personal data?The data controllers will comply with their legal obligations to
keep personal data up to date; to store and destroy it securely; to not collect
or retain excessive amounts of data; to keep personal data secure, and to
protect personal data from loss, misuse, unauthorised access and disclosure and
to ensure that appropriate technical measures are in place to protect personal
data.We use your personal data for some or all of the following
purposes:·
To enable us to meet all legal and statutory obligations (which
include maintaining and publishing our church electoral roll in accordance with
the Church Representation Rules);·
To carry out comprehensive safeguarding procedures (including due
diligence and complaints handling) in accordance with best safeguarding
practice from time to time with the aim of ensuring that all children and
adults-at-risk are provided with safe environments;·
To minister to you and provide you with pastoral and spiritual
care (such as visiting you when you are gravely ill or bereaved) and to
organise and perform ecclesiastical services for you, such as baptisms,
confirmations, weddings and funerals;·
To deliver the Church’s mission to our community, and to carry out
any other voluntary or charitable activities for the benefit of the public as
provided for in the constitution and statutory framework of each data
controller; ·
To administer the parish, deanery, archdeaconry and diocesan
membership records; ·
To fundraise and promote the interests of the Church and charity; ·
To maintain our own accounts and records;·
To process a donation that you have made (including Gift Aid
information);·
To seek your views or comments;·
To notify you of changes to our services, events and role holders;
·
To send you communications which you have requested and that may
be of interest to you.  These may include
information about campaigns, appeals, other fundraising activities;·
To process a grant or application for a role;·
To enable us to provide a voluntary service for the benefit of the
public in a particular geographical area as specified in our constitution; ·
Our processing may also include the use of CCTV systems for the
prevention and prosecution of crime. What
is the legal basis for processing your personal data?Most of our data is processed because it is necessary for our
legitimate interests, or the legitimate interests of a third party (such as
another organisation in the Church of England).  An example of this would be our safeguarding
work to protect children and adults at risk.  We will always take into account your
interests, rights and freedoms.Some of our processing is necessary for compliance with a legal
obligation.  We may also process data if it is necessary for the performance of
a contract with you, or to take steps to enter into a contract.  An example of this would be processing your
data in connection with the hire of any church facilities.Religious organisations are also permitted to process information
about your religious beliefs to administer membership or contact details.Where your information is used other than in accordance with one
of these legal bases, we will first obtain your consent to that use.Sharing
your personal dataYour personal data will be treated as strictly confidential.  It will only be shared with third parties
where it is necessary for the performance of our tasks or where you first give us
your prior consent.  It is likely that we
will need to share your data with some or all of the following (but only where
necessary):·
The appropriate bodies of the Church of England including the
other data controllers;·
Our agents, servants and contractors. For example, we may ask a
commercial provider to send out newsletters on our behalf, or to maintain our
database software.  We currently use the
following organisations to manage aspects of our online administrationo
Churchbuilder – www.churchbuilder.co.uk –
provides the database functionality for our website and web based
administration.o
Mailchimp – www.mailchimp.com –
helps us to send out regular church newsletters and updateso
Ticket Tailor - www.tickettailor.com – is
used to provide ticketing for events via the websiteo
Paypal – www.paypal.co.uk – is
used to process payments online for events and one off givingo
iZettle – www.izettle.com – is
used to allow us to process card payments for books, events etc using their
physical cardreader·
Other clergy or lay persons nominated or licensed by the bishops
of the Diocese of London to support the mission of the Church in our parish.  For example, our clergy are supported by our
area dean and archdeacon, who may provide confidential mentoring and pastoral
support.  Assistant or temporary
ministers, including curates, deacons, licensed lay ministers, commissioned lay
ministers or persons with Bishop’s Permissions may participate in our mission
in support of our regular clergy;·
Other persons or organisations operating within the Diocese of
London including, where relevant, the London Diocesan Board for Schools and
Subsidiary Bodies;·
On occasion, other churches with which we are carrying out joint
events or activities.How
long do we keep your personal data?We
will keep some records permanently if we are legally required to do so.  We may keep some other records for an extended
period of time. For example, it is current best practice to keep financial
records for a minimum period of 7 years to support HMRC audits.  In general, we will endeavour to keep data
only for as long as we need it.  This
means that we may delete it when it is no longer needed.Your
rights and your personal data You have the following rights with respect to your personal data:When exercising any of the rights listed below, in order to
process your request, we may need to verify your identity for your security.  In such cases we will need you to respond
with proof of your identity before you can exercise these rights.1.
The right to access information we hold on you·
At any point you can contact us to request the information we hold
on you as well as why we have that information, who has access to the
information and where we obtained the information from.  Once we have received your request we will
respond within one month. ·
There are no fees or charges for the first request but additional
requests for the same data may be subject to an administrative fee . 2.
The right to correct and update the information we hold on you·
If the data we hold on you is out of date, incomplete or
incorrect, you can inform us and your data will be updated. 3.
The right to have your information erased·
If you feel that we should no longer be using your data or that we
are illegally using your data, you can request that we erase the data we hold. ·
When we receive your request we will confirm whether the data has
been deleted or the reason why it cannot be deleted (for example because we
need it for our legitimate interests or regulatory purpose(s)). 4.
The right to object to processing of your data·
You have the right to request that we stop processing your data.
Upon receiving the request we will contact you and let you know if we are able
to comply or if we have legitimate grounds to continue to process your
data.  Even after you exercise your right
to object, we may continue to hold your data to comply with your other rights
or to bring or defend legal claims. 5.
The right to data portability·
You have the right to request that we transfer some of your data
to another controller. We will comply with your request, where it is feasible
to do so, within one month of receiving your request.6.
The right to withdraw your consent to the processing at any time
for any processing of data to which consent was sought.·
You can withdraw your consent easily by telephone, email, or by
post (see Contact Details below).7.
The right to object to the processing of personal data where
applicable.8.
The right to lodge a complaint with the Information Commissioner’s
Office.Transfer
of Data AbroadAny
electronic personal data transferred to countries or territories outside the EU
will only be placed on systems complying with measures giving equivalent
protection of personal rights either through international agreements or
contracts approved by the European Union.  Our website is also accessible from overseas
so on occasion some personal data (for example in a newsletter) may be accessed
from overseas.Further processingIf
we wish to use your personal data for a new purpose, not covered by this Notice,
then we will provide you with a new notice explaining this new use prior to
commencing the processing and setting out the relevant purposes and processing
conditions.  Where and whenever
necessary, we will seek your prior consent to the new processing.Contact DetailsPlease
contact us if you have any questions about this Privacy Notice or the information
we hold about you or to exercise all relevant rights, queries or complaints at:The
Data Controller, Grace Church, Muswell HillEmail:
churchoffice@gracech.org.ukYou can contact the Information Commissioners Office on 0303 123
1113 or via email (href=https://ico.org.uk/global/contact-us/email/)https://ico.org.uk/global/contact-us/email/ or at
the Information Commissioner's Office, Wycliffe
House, Water Lane, Wilmslow, Cheshire SK9 5AF.This policy was lasted
updated March 2020
Listen again
Download talks
